University Poster Collection, 1931-2014
University of Arizona Libraries, Special Collections
University Poster Collection, 1931-2014
MS 529
University of Arizona. Library. Special Collections
This is an artificial collection comprised of posters relating to The University of Arizona, and Northern Arizona University.
12 Linear feet
University of Arizona Libraries, Special Collections University of Arizona PO Box 210055 Tucson, AZ 85721-0055 Phone: 520-621-6423 Fax: 520-621-9733 URL: http://speccoll.library.arizona.edu/
Restrictions
There are no restrictions on this collection.
Accruals
Future accretions to the collection are expected.
Historical Note
Posters are cheap to produce, can be easily displayed in public as well as private areas, and use images and slogans that are easily understood by the masses. Due to these attributes, posters are used primarily as a tool of advertising and propaganda. Posters have their beginning in England as printed bills in the late 15th century. Typically these bills were typographical with accompanying wood cut images and promoted meetings and theater performances. With the increase of manufactured goods during the Industrial Revolution, the poster's stature as a tool of advertising experienced an upsurge. Alois Senefelder's invention of the lithographic process resulted in a cheaper and faster printing process that was quickly adopted by advertisers as well as artists. The public's interest in posters grew dramatically in France during the Art Nouveau movement of the late 19th century. Fine artists such as Alphonse Mucha and Henri de Toulousse-Lautrec incorporated lyrical and fantastic themes with typical advertising conventions to create posters that blurred the line between fine art and advertising which became immediate collector's items. The poster maintained its elevated stance as a tool of communication throughout the 20th century, being employed by governments during World War I and World War II as tools of spreading nationalistic propaganda as well as being utilized by private industries to sell goods and services.
Arrangement
This collection is organized into 2 series.
Series I: General University of Arizona Posters, 1931 - 2014
Series II: Northern Arizona University Posters, 1982-1984
Scope and Content Note
This collection contains two series. The first series contains posters from Special Collections exhibits, University of Arizona Library exhibits, The University of Arizona Poetry Center, University of Arizona Summer Session Classes, General University of Arizona Posters and Broadsides, and miscellaneous topics. The second series contains posters from the Northern Arizona University.
Access Terms
Northern Arizona University.
University of Arizona – Posters.
University of Arizona. Library. – Exhibitions.
University of Arizona. Library. Special Collections – Exhibitions.
University of Arizona. Poetry Center - Broadsides.
Container List
- Series 1: General University of Arizona Posters, 1931 - 2014, undated
  - Special Collections Exhibits, 2000 (Drawer 11, Folder 1)
  - Special Collections Exhibits, 2001 (Drawer 11, Folder 2)
  - Special Collections Exhibits, 2002 (Drawer 11, Folder 3)
  - Special Collections Exhibits, 2003 (Drawer 11, Folder 4)
  - Special Collections Exhibits, 2004 (Drawer 11, Folder 5)
  - Special Collections Exhibits, 2005 (Drawer 11, Folder 6)
  - Special Collections Exhibits, 2006 (Drawer 11, Folder 7)
  - Special Collections Exhibits, 2007 (Drawer 11, Folder 8)
  - Special Collections Exhibits, 2008-2014 (Drawer 11, Folder 9)
  - University of Arizona Library Exhibits, 1992-2002 (Drawer 12, Folder 1)
  - University of Arizona Poetry Center Posters, 1970-1990 (Drawer 12, Folder 2)
  - Summer Session Posters, 1931-1950 (Drawer 13, Folder 1)
  - College Lad and Lassie Posters, undated (Drawer 13, Folder 2)
  - General University of Arizona Posters and Broadsides, undated (Drawer 13, Folder 3)
  - Arts Posters, undated (Drawer 13, Folder 4)
  - Activities – Other, undated (Drawer 13, Folder 5)
  - General Posters – Southwest, undated (Drawer 13, Folder 6)
- Series 2: Northern Arizona University Posters, 1982-1984, undated
  - Northern Arizona University Posters, 1982-1984, undated (Drawer 13, Folder 7)